Good morning everybody.
As of today we will have done 100 daf דף daf in
Bava Kamma בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, so throw yourself a little party.
Today's daf דף daf is Kof Aleph ק"א. Kof Aleph. We pick
up with the Mishna משנה Mishna on Kof Amud Bet ק' עמוד
ב. Kof Amud Bet. And the first previous Mishna משנה Mishna had
spoken about
workers who damage the objects they've been given and they're liable and
they have to pay. It was maybe a type of Mazik מזיק.
Mazik. Interestingly though, a certain level of negligence was needed and we
had a whole discussion that if somebody's primary role vis-a-vis this object
is that of a workman or is that of a Shomer שומר,
Shomer, that that might actually put it in a different category than
Adam Hamazik אדם המזיק Adam Hamazik even when the object is damaged.
But anyway, that was sort of the background to this Mishna משנה
Mishna which fits more in our Perek פרק, Perek, because that was
just a straight case of damage. You know, you were banging in
the nail in the box and the box shattered. Now we're going
to get back to a case of Shinui שינוי, Shinui, but Shinui
שינוי Shinui not in the context of Gezela גזילה Gezela but in
the context of here a craftsman or worker working on some object
of yours. So let's take a look at the Mishna משנה. Mishna.
Hanotein tzemer latzaba הנותן צמר לצבע. Hanotein tzemer latzaba. So somebody gave
wool to a dyer. This has been quoted before, or this or
variations of this. Ve-hikdicho yoreh והקדיחו יורה. Ve-hikdicho yoreh. And the pot
scalded it, like the pot burnt it, you know, ruined it. Noten
lo d'mei tzemaro נותן לו דמי צמרו. Noten lo d'mei tzemaro. You
have to give him the cost of the wool. You know, this
is a continuation of the previous Mishna משנה, Mishna, whether it assumes
negligence, the degree of negligence needed, that's not being discussed. But the
point is it was damaged in the process of working with his
wool. It was destroyed. You pay for it. Fine, that's an easy
case. That's when it was essentially destroyed. Now, Tzeva'o ka'or צבעו כאור.
Tzeva'o ka'or. This does not mean like light. The Aleph here is
in place of an Ayin. If it was dyed in an inferior
with an inferior dye. So you used the right color, but you
used some inferior dye. And obviously so the resultant quality was not
as good. Im hashevach yoter al hayetzia noten lo et hayetzia אם
השבח יותר על היציאה נותן לו את היציאה. Im hashevach yoter al
hayetzia noten lo et hayetzia. Im hayetzia yoter al hashevach noten lo
et hashevach אם היציאה יותר על השבח נותן לו את השבח. Im
hayetzia yoter al hashevach noten lo et hashevach. So in this case,
it's not considered a Shinui שינוי. Shinui. Nobody discusses the possibility that
it's a Shinui שינוי Shinui and that you might take possession of
the object and pay him for the cost of the wool. Because
basically he said dye it red and you dyed it red. Okay,
but you did a poor job. All right, so it's not a
Shinui שינוי Shinui for you to say you now own the object.
Question is, how do you deal with the fact that you've created,
you know, that it would have been worth 200 dollars and because
you used a poor dye or you did a poor job it's
only worth 150 dollars? Okay,
so you know, what type of responsibility do you have? It's a
good question, right? I give you 100 dollars worth of wool and
50 dollars as your fee, and I'm expecting to get a 200
dollar product, and you come out with 150 dollar product. Right, what's
my recourse? Right, are you a Mazik מזיק? Mazik? I mean the
wool's worth more. Are you Kona קונה Kona with a Shinui שינוי?
Shinui? No you're not. So what's my recourse? So the Mishna משנה
Mishna says that you I have to pay you now the lesser
of the two, the lesser of your expenses, hayetzia היציאה, hayetzia, okay,
yetsia יציאה, yetsia, or of the amount that the wool improved. Now,
first of all, it would be very bizarre, you must have really
been a bad craftsman if your if the improvement of the wool
is less than the amount of effort you put in. Right? I
mean we've all done that or I've all done that in your
your home improvement projects. You spend more money and you actually make
your home worth less or whatever. You know, there are if you
don't know what you're doing, if you don't know what you're doing,
you can definitely have it that your expenses are more than the
increased value. Hopefully that's not normally the case, but maybe it is.
So I pay the guy I'm first going to read the Pshat
פשט Pshat of the Mishna משנה Mishna and then I'm going to
sort of tell you how Tosafot תוספות Tosafot reads it based on
Yerushalmi ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Okay. The Pshat פשט Pshat of the Mishna משנה
Mishna is I pay you the lesser of your expenses or of
the increase. So let's assume it's a normal case where your expenses
are less than the increase. So I contracted, I gave you 100
dollars worth of wool, I contracted a 50 dollar fee, and I
was expecting 200 dollars worth of wool. In the end, the wool
was worth only 150 dollars. Okay. But maybe your your actual fee
for your labor of that 50 dollars, right,
25 is your expenses and 25 is labor. So in that case
I'm only going to pay you for your expenses. You lost your
labor buddy. You should have created me a much better product so
I'm only going to pay you 25 bucks and I'm going to
get 150 dollars worth of wool. Am I making as much profit
as I thought I would make? I thought I would make 50
dollars profit. In this scenario, are people getting this scenario? I'm only
making 25 dollars worth of profit. Right? What? No, I gave him
100 dollars worth of wool, I paid him for his expenses but
not for his labor, so I paid him 25 and the wool
is worth
150. So the owner of the wool always wins. The owner of
the wool, I'm talking I'm the owner of the wool. I always
win. Well, okay, but meaning what he netted from the whole enterprise
was wool that was worth 25 more dollars than he put into
the whole enterprise. That's what I'm talking about, the money he made.
Okay? Yeah, but I'm talking about the owner, all right? So you
got your wool, okay? That's worth $100, okay? You would have paid
the worker $50 for his effort. Of that $50, okay, 25 is
expense and 25 is his fee, okay? And if he had done
the job right,
okay, so if he had done the job right, you were expecting
the wool would have been worth $200, so you would have made
a $50 profit, okay? But he did a lousy job, and now
the wool is really only worth $150. I don't know how to
indicate that. Okay. The wool is only worth $150. This is the
actual value of the wool, not your $200, which is what you
were hoping, right? But it's only worth 150. So, if you were
to pay him full, you'd come out having got no profit. So
what it says is, fine, pay him his expenses, don't pay him
his cost of labor, and then you'll at least have made $25.
That's if the improvement is greater than the expenses. Now, by the
way, even in that scenario, at least you made 25, you didn't
make 50, you made 25. But in that scenario, it's possible to
give scenarios where it's going to be, you'll make zero. Let's say
the resultant cost, the resultant value of the wool was $125, okay?
Then you pay him his expenses, or it's 130, let's say it's
130. You pay him his expenses, you made five bucks out of
it, okay? So you're starting to make less and less, okay? Let's
say the resultant value of the wool is $120. So that's the
case in the גמרא Gemara where the משנה Mishnah where it says
אם היציאה, Im HaYetzi'ah, the $25 is more than the שבח. shevach.
The increased value is $20 here, right? So the יציאה, Yetzi'ah, the
expense is more than the שבח. shevach. So then you just pay
him for the increase, $20, which means you're not going to lose
any money off of it, but in that case, you made zero.
You were hoping to get a $50 profit out of this enterprise,
okay? So you're going to make zero out of that. Now, there's
a way, right? So I mean, as long as there's some improvement,
which is what we're assuming, okay? Even if it's only worth $105,
okay? So you don't have to pay him his fee, you don't
have to pay him his expenses, but you do pay at least
the amount that it improved, five dollars. So at the end of
the day, you're going to make zero. You break even. Yeah, you
break even. You break even. Okay, so that's the פשט pshat of
this משנה. Mishnah. You either pay him his expenses and you're not
going to get the full amount of profit you were hoping, but
you'll get maybe some profit, okay? Or if the value was very,
very little
compared to his, you know, comparable to his expenses, you're going to
pay for the increased value and you're going to make zero off
the whole transaction. And that's if that beautiful $100 of raw wool
as a result of this is now devalued to $75? Then he
pays as a מזיק. mazik. That's the first half of the משנה.
Mishnah. That's נזק. nezek. That's the first half of the משנה. Mishnah.
So the thing is here, right? The גמרא, Gemara, משנה Mishnah doesn't
tell you what is the mechanism that explains this. I mean, this
seems like a reasonable way of dealing with it, right? But you
know, but like if the guy isn't a מזיק, mazik, he isn't
a גזלן, gazlan, he isn't a קונה בשינוי, koneh b'shinui, he's like
a worker that did not do what you hired him for. So
what the חז"ל Chazal basically come and they say is, well, then
we're going to have to in that case basically read into the
contract, adjust the terms of the contract. And we're going to say
that if he does it in a bad way, that actually now
the result is, you know, now let's say you were hoping it
was going to be worth 150 and it was worth 145. Like,
I mean, you know, presumably there's a point in which he did
everything right and it's still not, you know, things didn't work out
perfectly. That's not what we're talking about. We're talking about that he
actually did vary from what he was supposed to do. He used
the wrong dye. Okay, he wasn't מזיק mazik it, he wasn't גזלן
gazlan it, it wasn't a שינוי, shinui, but he did something wrong
and it did not result in the same quality. So חז"ל Chazal
are saying is we're going now re-read the terms of the contract
and say, and say that you only owe him the lesser, you
don't pay him for his work because his work was garbage, but
he did have out-of-pocket expenses. So you only pay him for the
lesser of his out-of-pocket expenses or for the improved value of the
object. So yes, you're not going to make as much profit, but
you're not going to lose any money and he's going to lose
his labor and that's like a reasonable פשרה. peshara. Like again, I
don't know if this is a דין, din, but this is sort
of the what חז"ל Chazal imposed on this. Yes, Charlie.
So it's a חידוש chiddush to say that the laborer gets anything
because he completely screwed up. He doesn't get anything for his labor,
he only gets for his expenses, his out-of-pocket expenses. But in secular
law, such a contractor wouldn't even get that. He'd have to eat
the whole thing because he completely screwed up and did not produce
the work that was under contract. Yeah, but there's a question about
degrees. a variation, right? We're going to get to the next part
of the משנה Mishna where he actually did the wrong color dye.
Here, it wasn't that he actually did a complete variation, he just
did an inferior job in the job he was supposed to do.
I am sure that there's a lot of complicated like secular law
about this case, okay? Right? You understand it's not like... it's not
like you were supposed to, you know, fix the rear fender and
he fixed the front fender or whatever something like, you know, he
did something completely wrong, right? It was that like it's not 100%,
you know, you didn't make the car look like it was new,
it was supposed to come out looking new. So do I owe
you nothing? Do I owe you something but not as much as
we agreed upon, right? I mean so I have no idea what
the answer is, but there's like... I don't think it's as clear-cut
what the answer should be in that case. Yes, but it's not
a שינוי. Shinuy. I mean like you know if before when I
gave it to him was this piece of wool, I wouldn't say
this... Oh no, it's... it's שינוי Shinuy that it was undyed wool
and it's dyed, but because it's dyed black and that was following
the directions of the owner, so then it's not considered a שינוי
Shinuy to have been different from out... you know you're right. It's
a שינוי Shinuy from what it was but not a שינוי Shinuy
in the sense of taking it away from the owner and something
different from the owner, yes. We're not calling the tradesman פושע. Poshea.
We might be, but it's not מזיק Mazik because the object isn't
worth less than it was. It's a lack of the improvement to
the degree we were hoping, and you know, and then the question
becomes so what becomes now in terms of our... my contractual agreement
to pay him for his work? But no, he might be a
פושע, Poshea, but in the first case the wool was destroyed, he
was a מזיק. Mazik. Here you're not a מזיק, Mazik, it's just
not worth as much as we were hoping, right? So this is
the basic פשט Pshat about expenses versus improvement, and you're not paying
for the labor. Now I want to say that תוספות Tosafos has
a read of a ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. תוספות Tosafos sort of admits it's
not פשט Pshat of ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, but he quotes the way the
רי Ri read the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that basically says that I won't
sort of try to work it in with you with all the
language of the משנה, Mishna, but what he basically tries to read
is that what you're paying him is for... is that we basically
figure out what profit you would have made, okay? And then we
try to... we make the arrangement as such that you're able as...
if at all possible, to retain that amount of profit. So in
this scenario, you would have made fifty dollars profit, okay? So תוספות
Tosafos says in that case you pay him nothing. You got now
wool worth a hundred and fifty dollars, okay? If it had all
gone right, you would have paid him fifty, it would have been
worth two hundred, you would have made a fifty dollar profit. In
this case, you pay him nothing, so you had a hundred dollar
wool and you ended up with a fifty dollar profit, okay? And
then basically what תוספות Tosafos says, and I won't again try to
work it into the words of the משנה, Mishna, but just the
basic conceptual approach is you figure out how much profit you should
have made if everything had gone right and basically you pocket that,
and if there's anything left over, you pay him. Okay, now you
don't... he doesn't pay you for loss of profit, right? If you
were to make fifty dollars and now even if you pay him
zero, you're still only making forty, fine, you've only made forty. Okay?
But you start with the idea that you deduct the profit that
you would have made from the contractual arrangement, okay? And then you
pay him the difference. Okay? That's different, that's a different reading of
what we said. But what תוספות Tosafos wants to do is ensure
as much as possible that you're able to get the profit you
would have deserved. That's putting more pressure on the artisan. Yeah, clearly.
Okay, this case we're just saying like you don't have to pay
him for his labor if he screwed up, but you're probably... there's
a good chance you're going to be... not coming out with as
much profit as you had hoped, okay? תוספות Tosafos starts the other
way. Like that guy might even lose his out-of-pocket expenses, okay? Because
you're entitled if under normal
circumstances everything had gone right, it would have been worth X amount
more, you're entitled to come away with that amount of profit. He
won't have to pay for it directly, again, if he's not a
מזיק, Mazik, but indirectly he caused you to not have that profit,
so you get to deduct that from any money you would have
paid him. Yeah, again, only conceptually, that's harder to prove, no? In
other words, I'd have to be able to prove that the market
would have absolutely enabled me to get this amount... Right. I mean
but even here when we're talking about how much is the שבח,
Shevach, how do you assess the שבח? Shevach? You have to figure
out what would the market... Right. Clearly, there's always going to be
that problem. What's the פסק הלכה Psak Halacha then? I don't know.
It depends... I mean, I haven't sort of seen how this plays
out
in bottom-line פסק הלכה, Psak Halacha, but my guess is not תוספות'ס
Tosafos's way. It's clearly not פשט Pshat and even תוספות Tosafos admits
that it's not פשט. Pshat. But it was interesting because you had
the Michael question, so what's the הלכה? Halacha? But it's important to
notice where he's coming from, right? It's a different perspective. Okay, let's
continue with the משנה. Mishna.
Okay.
Now, לצבוע לו אדום וצבעו שחור Litzboa Lo Adom Utzvao Shachor how
about if there was a more clear, not just inferior job, but
violating the instructions of the owner and you produce an end result
like a different color? Then we can start talking about the idea
of a שינוי. Shinuy. Okay, now again, it's a שינוי Shinuy not
in the context of גזילה, Gezeilah, but this... is what this is
doing in our מסכתא. masechtah. Okay, לצבוע לו אדום וצבעו שחור, litzboa
lo adom utzvao shachor, שחור וצבעו אדום shachor v'tzvao adom or black
and he did red? רבי מאיר אומר נותן לו דמי צמרו. Rabbi
Meir omer nosin lo d'mei tzemoro. Rabbi Meir says that's like מזיק.
mazik. Okay, you're קונה koneh with a שינוי shinui and he just
pays you for the wool. Okay, now רבי יהודה אומר אם השבח
יתר על היציאה נותן לו את היציאה ואם היציאה יתרה על השבח
נותן לו את השבח. Rabbi Yehuda omer im hashevach yeter al hayetzia
nosin lo es hayetzia v'im hayetzia yeter al hashevach nosin lo es
hashevach. It's the same as the previous law. You're not קונה koneh
with שינוי. shinui. Okay, he did not do the job you had
hired him for. The improvement wasn't as much as you were hoping,
so you pay the lesser of expenses and improvement. Okay, so basically
the debate is when the אומן uman acts out of his instructions,
out of, you know, and he makes it a different object than
you were hoping, not just inferior. Okay, is there a concept of
קונה koneh with a שינוי? shinui? And that's what it's doing here.
The מסכתא masechtah starts with שינוי shinui by גזילה. gezeilah. Does שינוי
shinui apply here as well? Jenna, you had a question. Yeah, but
the weird thing about Rabbi Meir's answer is that when you're talking
about dying different colors, maybe the accidental color is worth more. Right,
a guy could have a great little business model. Somebody comes in
with some high-quality wool, I'm going to sort of dye it the
wrong color, I'll make the profit off of... Okay, you probably won't
stay in business too long, but that's absolute correct and that's worth
the point that it's not clear according to Rabbi Meir and Rabbi
Yehuda which one is more מחמיר machmir or מיקל, meikel, which one
is better for the owner of the wool and which one is
better for the professional, right? Like it could work out different in
different cases. So, you know, it's not coming from a place of
'I want to protect the interests of the manufacturer, I want to
protect the interests of the guy with the, you know, of the
client' because there's no way to determine who's going to come out
better. It's a conceptual question of 'Are you קונה koneh with a
שינוי shinui or not? Is שינוי shinui relevant in this case or
not?' Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי כאור?
Mai ka'ur? What does it mean כאור? ka'ur? Again, רש"י Rashi says
it's really like with an ayin, inferior. Okay, what would be the
scenario of that? אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר בר חנה, Amar
Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar bar Chana, כלבוס, kalbus, which is very
helpful. מאי כלבוס? Mai kalbus? אמר רבה בר שמואל, Amar Rabba bar
Shmuel, קפרא דדודי, kafra d'dudi, the sort of the gunk on the
bottom of the pot. Okay, so you use like inferior dye, the
dye, you know, I don't know the process, crazy things. Right, there's
some process, right, of taking, you know, these whatever they are, like
gallnuts, I guess, if you're making like a black dye or whatever
and you put... you know, you immerse them in water and you
know and that creates a dye. So somehow in some time of
that process, some of the stuff, there's a residue. So you use
the residue, you don't use the higher quality or just the standard
quality. Okay, תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. הנותן עצים לחרש לעשות מהם כסא
ועשה מהם ספסל. Hanosen eitzim lacharas l'asos mehem kisei v'asa mehem safsal.
Okay,
you made... you gave wood to say, 'Here, make a chair,' and
he made a stool. ספסל ועשה מהם כסא, safsal v'asa mehem kisei,
a stool... it's more like a bench. You're right, maybe it's more
like a bench. Okay, a bench, could it be both? What's a
stool? What's a stool in here? Stool is like a three-legged... got
three legs... I know what it is, what's the Hebrew word for
it? Sorry. I don't know what you're asking me. Okay, you got
a ספסל. safsal. Stool is not a bench. They say bench. Okay,
I thought it was a stool.
Okay, anyway, fine, whatever.
שלשה... shlosha... Alright, we will go with bench. Okay, you're definitely right,
Michael, that there are stories about people sitting on a bench, four
people sitting, fifth person comes along. Okay, I think in modern Hebrew...
I don't know, what do I know? ספסל ועשה מהם כסא. safsal
v'asa mehem kisei. Okay, or a stool and he made a chair.
I said stool again. A bench. Shh, quiet everybody. A bench and
he made a chair. רבי מאיר אומר נותן לו דמי עציו. Rabbi
Meir omer nosin lo d'mei eitzov. Rabbi Meir says,
just like the question of red and black, this is even more
radical than red and black. You're קונה koneh with the שינוי, shinui,
pay him for the wood. רבי יהודה אומר לא אם השבח יתר
על היציאה נותן לו את היציאה ואם היציאה יתרה על השבח נותן
לו את השבח. Rabbi Yehuda omer no, im hashevach yeter al hayetzia
nosin lo es hayetzia v'im hayetzia yeter al hashevach nosin lo es
hashevach. No, you're not קונה koneh with a שינוי, shinui, you're just
a craftsman that did not sort of do the end result as
desired, but you weren't a מזיק, mazik, and you pay the guy
the lesser of expenses and the improved value.
Okay, ומודה רבי מאיר, u'modeh Rabbi Meir, now Rabbi Meir agrees... I'm
going to have to split you two up. ומודה רבי מאיר אם
נתן עצים לחרש לעשות מהם כסא נאה ועשה מהם כסא כאור. u'modeh
Rabbi Meir im nassan eitzim lacharas l'asos mehem kisei na'eh v'asa mehem
kisei ka'ur.
But now again, this is like the using the inferior dye. Rabbi
Meir agrees that there are some things which are not considered a
שינוי. shinui. If you said, 'I want you to make a gorgeous
chair, like a throne' and they made like a little, you know,
plain one. ספסל נאה ועשה מהם ספסל כאור, safsal na'eh v'asa mehem
safsal ka'ur, to make a beautiful bench and he did a... you
know, he did an inferior job. In that case, you're not קונה
koneh with a שינוי shinui and you just pay the difference. Okay,
you pay the minimum. The smaller of the two. אם השבח יתר
על היציאה נותן לו דמי היציאה ואם היציאה יתרה על השבח נותן
לו דמי השבח. im hashevach yeter al hayetzia nosin lo d'mei hayetzia
v'im hayetzia yeter al hashevach nosin lo d'mei hashevach. Okay, so that
is just a nice application taking the exact issue of the משנה
Mishnah and going from colors to a more radical change of form,
okay, and it's the same basic issue. If it's basically the same
object... object, same color, same whatever, but inferior, everybody agrees that you're
קונה בשינוי konei b'shinui and it's the lesser of the two, and
the question is when it's a different type of an object, yes.
And the שבח, shevach, like you know, take into account my advertising,
for instance, let's say I'm a merchant, right, and I sell the
high-end stuff, right, now there's this like, you know, little nothing there
that's be harder for me to sell, so I've got to go
through more advertising expenses or whatever it is, do they take into
account... I mean, you're... it's a good question. You're right. Meaning when
I figure out the cost, right, is there like a wholesale cost
and a retail cost? Like if I wanted to get rid of
this right away, you know, I could get X amount for it.
You know, sure I could try and keep it in my store
for a year and finally somebody will buy it at the retail
cost. The other thing would have sold much quicker. Yeah, that's a
very good question, how you figure out... yeah, those are all excellent
questions, right? I mean, you know, again, I had this... I have
this friend who said to me, you know, that you see in
the גמרא, Gemara, like he says like half of law is not
figuring out like, you know, the legal case, it's not figuring out
like the law, it's like figuring out like, you know, like these
פרטים, pratim, like how you determine the facts and how you assess
the facts, whatever, you know, like almost all of that is always
missing from the גמרא, Gemara, right, and that would make all the
difference in these cases. Okay, anyway, איבעיא להו: iba'ya l'hu: יש שבח
סמנים על הצמר או אין שבח סמנים על הצמר. yesh shevach samanim
al hatzemer o ein shevach samanim al hatzemer.
So similar to these are some great broad conceptual questions, you know,
that the בבלי Bavli asks, you know, in like yesterday or two
days ago we had the question about אומן קונה בשבח כלי, uman
koneh b'shevach kli,
right, the improvement of the thing before it's handed over, is that
owned by the person who created it, right? You know, is there
a sense of, you know, if you create something you own it
until you actually hand it over. Well here there's a question of...
it's a different conceptual question. I dye your wool, okay, is that
considered like my dye is still present in your wool? So what's
the relevance of that question, right? In the way the גמרא Gemara
is going to rephrase this in a minute, to maybe... this might
help you is: חזותא מילתא היא או לא. chazuta milta hi o
lo. Is the color of something, the appearance of something, is that
really like the object is physically present? Like do I say what
I have here is a shirt and there's also I also have
some blue dye together in my shirt, right, or is this just
a blue shirt? It's not like there's dye that's still present here.
Okay, now what's the נפקא מינה nafka mina of that question? Wait,
is it like for ציצית tzitzis questions, right? Well, right, so okay,
so let's take a look. So יש שבח סמנים על הצמר או
אין שבח סמנים על הצמר. yesh shevach samanim al hatzemer o ein
shevach samanim al hatzemer. Is the improvement of the dye still present
in the wool? So היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא
דגזל סמנים ודקינהו וטרינהו, iileima degazal samanim v'dakinu v'tarinu, I stole from
Michael some... some... again the word isn't spices, I don't know what
the word is, or not fragrances, dyes, but they're... but it's... but
it's not when we think of dye we think of like the
liquid. I basically stole from you the... right, the... the actual vegetable,
you know, object, the grain, the seed... let's say ingredients, that's helpful.
Okay, anyway, I stole from you the, you know, the various sort
of raw materials to make the dye, okay, ודקינהו וטרינהו, v'dakinu v'tarinu,
and I stomped on them and I sort of immersed them in
water to produce the dye, וצבע בהן, utzva bahem, and then I
used it to dye something with those. And the quest... well, and
then the question is, could I say, oh look, that's still your
dye over there, take it back. So the גמרא Gemara says well
no, typically משום דקנינהו בשינוי. mishum dekaninu b'shinui.
When I went through that process of stomping on them and immersing
them, I took possession of it right away. It's not the question
of when the dye hits the wool, I...
I already totally took possession of it at that moment with the
שינוי. shinui. So אלא, ella, so... I lost my place... דקנינהו בשינוי.
dekaninu b'shinui. לא צריכה דגזל סמנים שרויים. lo tzricha degazal samanim sheruyim.
Okay, no, I actually stole from Michael here the actual like liquid
dye, okay, they were already immersed. I stole the liquid dye, וצבע
בהן, v'tzava bahem, and then I went then and I used this
liquid dye to dye my wool. So what's the question? וצבע בהן
מאי? v'tzava bahem mai? יש שבח סמנים אגבי צמר, yesh shevach samanim
agabei tzemar, so do we say Michael's dye is still present in
my wool? דאמר ליה הב לי סמנאי דשקילתינהו, d'amar lei hav li
samnai d'shakiltinu,
and then Michael can say to me, 'Hey, Dov, you know, your...
my dye is on your wool, give me back my dye,' and
then he's going to take my wool with it. And you would
have to pay the cost of... Well, okay, let's just sort of
see where we go with this, okay. או דילמא אין שבח סמנים
אגבי הצמר, o dilma ein shevach samanim agabei hatzemer, or maybe no,
your dye is no longer present, all you have left is color,
your dye isn't present, דאמר ליה לית לך גבאי ולא מידי, d'amar
lei leit lach gabei v'lo midei, and I could tell Michael, 'Ha,
I don't have your stuff, go... you know... go take a long
walk off a short pier.' And then what? So the גמרא Gemara
says, so the גמרא Gemara says what are you talking about? I
still stole it! I can't get rid of Michael. אמרי, amri, ואין
שבח סמנים אגבי צמר, v'ein shevach samanim agabei tzemar,
even if the dye isn't physically present, מי מצי אמרת ליה לית
לך גבאי ולא מידי, mi matzi amrit lei leit lach gabei v'lo
midei, how could I tell Michael 'go fly a kite, you don't...
I don't owe you anything'? נימא ליה הב לי סמנאי דאפסדתינהו, neima
lei hav li samnai d'afsadtinu,
Michael can say 'fine, you don't have my dye, so it's not
physically present, so you... so you destroyed it, so pay me for
it.' So either way, it's not like in one case I have
to pay him and in the other case I don't have to
pay him. That's not a relevant... there's no possibility however you come
out on this question that I get away from paying Michael. I
stole his stuff, okay? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא פשיטא, ella
pshita,
let's reverse it. אין שבח סמנים על גבי צמר, Ein shevach samanim
al gabbei tzemer, the dye isn't considered physically present, ובעי שלומי ליה,
u'ba shilumei lei, so Michael says you stole my dye, it's no
longer present, pay me for it. It's a hundred dollars, pay me
for it. או דלמא יש שבח סמנים על גבי צמר, O deilma
yesh shevach samanim al gabbei tzemer, or no, the dye is still
present, it's in the wool, it's present in the wool, ואמר ליה
המנך קמך, v'amar lei hamancha kamach,
I say Michael, I'm not paying you a hundred dollars, you want
your dye? It's still there. שקלינו, shaklinoo, go take it. Okay, try
to take it off of the wool. Okay, I didn't steal it,
it's right there, it's yours, just take it. So the גמרא Gemara
says שקלינו, shaklinoo, what do you mean take it? במאי שקלי, Bimai
shaklei, how's he going to get his dye off of the wool?
בצפן, B'tzappan, so he's going to use some type of dye remover,
that's what צפן tzappan is.
צפן אבוייה עברא, Tzappan avoya avra, it'll destroy the dye and he
won't have anything. So השבה לא עביד, hashava lo avid, I didn't
return it to him. So I can't say to Michael it's still
there, just take it. It can't be taken. אלא, Ella, now what
could you say? I could say take it with the wool, but
why would I want to do that? I'm going to lose the
wool. Okay, so what again would be the נפקא מינה nafka mina
of this question? אלא הכא במאי עסקינן, Ella hacha b'mai askinan, what's
the case? כגון דגזל צמר וסמנים דחד, k'gon d'gazal tzemer v'samanim d'chad,
fine, I stole Michael's wool and I stole his dye. Okay, because
obviously in the other case it was my wool and if the
dye was present I don't want to give him my wool, right?
So, you know, what's the נפקא מינה nafka mina of the whole
thing? Presumably I would just pay you for the dye. So right,
presumably I would just pay you for the dye. So we have
to have a case where it makes a difference. So the case
will be it's Michael's wool, I stole Michael's wool and Michael's dye.
דגזל צמר וסמנים דחד וצבעו להו צמר בהני סמנים, d'gazal tzemer v'samanim
d'chad v'tzav'u l'hu tzemer b'hanei samanim, and I dyed Michael's wool with
his dye. And I figured like I was going to go ahead
and sell it and make a profit. וקמהדר ליה ניהליה לצמר, v'ka
mahadar lei nihalei l'tzemer,
then I have a pang of conscience or I get caught and
I return now Michael the dyed wool to him. Have I returned
to him everything I stole? Okay, I stole dye, I stole wool,
I returned to him the dyed wool. I returned to you everything.
Okay, I don't have to tell you take the dye off the
wool. I'm giving you both. I'm giving you both of them back.
איבעיא, Ibay'ei, I make more out of it. Oh, so that's what
the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. יש שבח סמנים על גבי
הצמר Yesh shevach samanim al gabbei hatzemer וקמהדר ליה סמנים וצמר, v'ka
mahadar lei samanim v'tzemer, do we say the dye is still there
and now I've, you know, done my obligation, I've returned both to
him? או דלמא אין שבח סמנים על גבי צמר, O deilma ein
shevach samanim al gabbei tzemer, or maybe the dye is no longer
present, וצמר מהדר ליה סמנים לא מהדר ליה, v'tzemer mahadar lei samanim
lo mahadar lei, and I've only returned to him the wool, not
the dye, and I still owe him for the dye. So the
גמרא Gemara says you owe him for the
dye, אמאי תיפוק ליה דיקרו ניהליה בדמי, amai teipokei lei d'ya'akrei nihalei
b'damei, the wool is now worth more. Okay, so if it's that
the dye is present, I've been יוצא, yotzei, I returned both. If
the dye isn't present, now this gets back to stuff we learned
earlier. I steal something from somebody and I improve it as the
גזלן, gazlan, I steal their cow, I improve their cow, it gets
bigger, gets fatter, I return it. If you remember the הלכה halacha
before, it might have been based on תקנת השבים, takanas hashavim, it
might have been based on קנין גזילה, kinyan gezeila, but whatever it
was based on, I return with the improved object, the person actually
owes me for the improvement, right? People were joking that's a great
business model. Okay, but okay, that's the הלכה. halacha. So I stole
his wool, I stole his dye, I improved the value of the
wool. Presumably, right, it wouldn't be a good business if the improved
value wasn't worth more than the dye itself. So the dye was
worth 25, the improved value is worth 50. So I return it
to Michael, Michael says give me my dye. I say give me
the 50 dollars that I improved the wool. Okay, and at the
end of the day Michael's still going to owe me 25 dollars
because I now, you know, so in that case if it's יש
שבח סמנים, yesh shevach samanim, okay, I return it, and if it's
אין שבח סמנים ein shevach samanim and I owe him for the
dye but I'm also entitled to the improved value of the wool,
I also am not going to have to pay him anything. Presumably
that's even more than the dye was worth. You had a question?
Yes, that's the same case where it's both his wool and his
dye? Yes. The first case where it's his dye, isn't that the
wood plank and the wood beam in the house case? Oh,
yeah, it might be and that's sort of like what the גמרא
Gemara was assuming that you wouldn't return the wool in that case
and you just pay him for it. Yeah. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says לא צריכא דזיל טיוא. lo tzricha d'zil tiva.
Okay, now the case is here that the cost of, you know,
the way רש״י Rashi says it is that the cost of the
dyed wool, the market has gone down. Okay, so basically I stole
from Michael wool worth 100 and dye worth 25. And under normal
circumstances I would have dyed it and the end result would have
been 150 dollars worth of wool,
but the market has gone down since then and right now the
end result is less than that. It's only 100, the wool even
with the 25 dollars worth of dye, what used to be 25
dollars worth of dye, is only 110. So here's my question. I'm
sorry, so dyed wool's worth I stole 100 dollars worth of wool,
25, right, because the value of dye has gone down. You I
decided to return it six months later or even two days later,
the market plummeted. Okay, and right now dye is worth less and
dyed wool is worth less and everything is worth less. Okay, the
market plummeted. So if the dye is still there, I return to
him the physical object. It's like הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha.
Doesn't matter what the value is, I return to you
the physical
object. If however the dye isn't present, then I've returned him wool
now, dyed wool, with an improved value of five dollars or ten
dollars, but I stole dye worth fifty dollars or twenty-five dollars, that's
no longer present. So I never returned the dye, and I'm gonna
have to pay him the difference. Okay, so that is the question:
if the dye is present, I've returned everything. If the dye isn't
present, then I have to pay him for the value of the
dye minus minus the,
you know, the improved value of the wool. Why not say this
is a שינוי קונה shinui koneh in this case? Of the dye?
Yeah. Well that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying, is that is
this considered a שינוי shinui in the dye? I mean I think
it is, I mean obviously it is. I can't see, I don't
know if obviously it is. I mean I can't figure out in
the גמרא Gemara what degree of a change of something is a
שינוי, shinui, you know? I mean I like, sometimes the גמרא Gemara
says small things are and big things aren't, it's like I don't
know. But the גמרא, Gemara, but look, part of the point is
that this is where dye normally goes, dye doesn't have, its dye's
purpose is not to sort of live independently, right? It's to go
to color something, and if you can see the result, so the
גמרא Gemara says to what degree is that really a change in
it, you know? Now, but I understand the question. I mean intuitively
of course the dye isn't present, like the dye has undergone, even
if somehow the physical essence of it is present, it can't, how
to not call this, I understand. You look at it and you
say oh this is the wool with blue dye, right, exactly. I
understand, I understand. It's like, yes, intuitively it's a total שינוי השם
shinui hashem etc., I agree with you, yes. See, I mean the
way I've been thinking about it, tell me if this is what
you, because from the point of view of the wool, it's really
a
שינוי. shinui. Right. Although, although it's not clear that it's clearly a
שינוי shinui wool. Is raw wool and dyed wool a different thing?
I mean it is true that our משנה Mishna sort of assumes
black wool versus red wool is a שינוי. shinui.
But this is assuming, but this is assuming that you're returning the
wool. So I don't know if the גמרא Gemara is assuming that
the wool's a שינוי. shinui. If the wool's a שינוי, shinui, why
are you returning the wool?
But yes, that's the question to ask as well: is dyed wool
a שינוי shinui from the plain wool? So I've been looking up
dyeing on the internet, of course, and dyeing, there's two types of
colors for
fabrics: pigment, which is basically painting a garment, and in dyeing, it's
actually a chemical reaction between the dye and the yarn or the
fabric, and it's not the same thing in, and it's literally not
the same thing anymore. So you mean even physically it's different? Physically
it's a different, right, I assume we have, look, it's like the
difference between, like, you know, painting a table and staining a table,
right? So dye, I think, is basically like staining. It gets absorbed
into the material, it's not this coat, it's not this coat on
the surface of something, right? So I agree, logically you would say
that that's a real שינוי. shinui. A, it's not as considered physically
present, it's not like a coat laying on the top, and it's
a real שינוי, shinui, and I agree, is it a שינוי shinui
in the wool? It certainly should be a שינוי shinui in the
dye. I understand. The intuition here is to say אין שבח סמנים
על גבי צמר. ein shevach samanim al gabei tzemer. Yes, Jenna. Well
it's also here because when you have a big vat of dye
and you dye one piece of wool, you still have dye left
over. So the scenario would have to be is that I used
up all the dye. I took a little bit of dye, right,
you know, right. But okay, that is though the question. I understand
the intuition here, I agree with it, that logically this thing has
undergone a שינוי. shinui. But that's the question: do I return the
dyed wool, what? I'm sorry, you dropped a good word just a
second ago. Maybe סממנים sammanim is translated as pigment. Okay, that's probably
a good a better word, but
okay, okay. So anyway that's the scenario: I stole the dye and
the wool, I dyed the wool, am I, have I returned them
when I give dyed wool back? Or do we have to figure
out the whole dollar value here about the difference because I didn't
really return the dye. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
דזיפתא De-ziphta צבעא. tziv'a. ואי
בעית אימא, Ve-i ba'it eima, if you want, another scenario, כגון דצבעא
בהו קופא. Kegon de-tziv'a behu kupa. So what I did was I
used it and and I painted, now רש"י Rashi says קופא kupa
is a monkey, okay.
תוספות Tosafot says if you painted a monkey, that's like you're a
מזיק mazik on the dye, like you know that's like destroying it.
So תוספות Tosafot says you painted a basket, okay. So if I
painted a basket, that's that's an easier version, and that's just another
scenario where I stole Michael's basket, I stole his paint, I painted
his basket, but obviously, but in that case the end result of
the object is worth less than the raw materials, because that was
high quality dye that should have been used for wool, etc. Instead
I used it on a painted basket, people are not gonna pay
a lot more than a plain basket. Okay, so according to תוספות'ס
Tosafot's read, which we'll go with, that's just another version, rather than
saying the market fell down, you know, the market values changed, it's
another version where I'm returning the painted object to Michael, but the
end result is worth less than the raw materials. So is it
like I returned the raw materials or not in that case? Okay,
that's scenario number two. רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, one minute, what's the
question? Wait,
we're trying to frame this only in terms of monetary value. So
this is like a- say it was a monkey, right? You know,
and the guy says, "What'd you do to my monkey?" and isn't
that a damage? Like I don't want- well, that's what תוספות Tosafot
says, although it's not a damage to the monkey, just take a
bath. But to the dye. No, I meant to the- oh, it's
not permanent you're saying. Yeah, yeah. Okay, but תוספות Tosafot says it's
certainly a damage to the
dye. Okay, so רבינא אמר הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דצמר דחד וסמנים
דחד. Ravina amar hacha bemai askinan kigon detzamer dechad vesamanim dechad. No,
no, no. Here's the case. It's not a גזילה gezeila case. Okay.
Michael has a bag of- has wool. David has dye. I come
to visit them with my pet monkey Curious George. This is why
רש״י Rashi said- there- I think what inclined רש״י Rashi to say
קופא kufa meant a monkey rather than a basket is because we're
about to talk about a קוף. kof. Okay, there was no גזילה
gezeila here. Okay, a monkey came along.
ואתא קוף וצבעיה להוא צמר בהנך סמנים. veata kof vetzavaya lehu tzamer
behanach samanim.
And it was getting into trouble, and like Curious George will do,
and he basically- it's totally out of Curious George, though. Like, anyway.
He basically mixed Michael's wool with David's dye. So now the question
is- so there's no recourse to the monkey, okay? So, I mean,
I guess if I'm the owner of the monkey you could talk
to me about like a- we go to the first half of
בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, but it's a wild monkey, forget that. So
here's the question. יש שבח סמנים על גבי צמר דאמר ליה הבו
לי סמנאי דגבך נינהו? yesh shevach samanim al gabei tzamer d'amar lei
havu li samnai degabach ninhu? Does Michael get to say to David,
you know, okay, no one of us did anything wrong, but my
dye is still present, give me back my dye? And, you know,
and David will have to then, if he can't physically remove the
dye and give it back, which he obviously can't, he'll have to
pay Michael for the cost of the dye, because it's like Michael's
dye is in David's yard. או דילמא אין שבח סמנים על גבי
צמר ואמר ליה לית לך גבאי ולא כלום? o dilma ein shevach
samanim al gabei tzamer veamar lei leit lach gabai velo klum? And
David says, no, there's no dye left here, the dye disappeared, I
don't have anything of yours. Now תוספות Tosafot asks a very good
question. תוספות Tosafot says you might remember from the first half of
בבא קמא Bava Kamma that if without any fault I derive benefit
from you, my animal goes and falls into your yard and it
got cushioned by falling on your fruit, or it ate your fruit
in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, I don't have to pay you for
the value of the fruit, but I do have to pay you
for some of the fact that I derived benefit at- from your
object and at a loss to you, and it seems conceptually like
I have that benefit. So תוספות Tosafot says even if the dye
isn't seen as present, if David's wool now is worth twenty dollars
more, it's like he has twenty dollars of benefit that he got
from Michael and he has to pay him that twenty dollars, right?
Now maybe in a way again, like, you know, at a discounted
rate or something, okay, but תוספות Tosafot says like even if the
dye isn't physically present, why shouldn't he owe Michael some money? And
then he asks some interesting questions about maybe if he didn't- he
or his animal didn't do anything, it was just sort of like
an act of God, an act of monkey, you know, whatever that
happened it may be he doesn't have to pay Michael for the
fact that his property is now worth more. And there's no גנב
ganav in the total- like is out of the picture now? What?
No גנב ganav in this case. Okay. We said that. No, no,
this- no, this last scenario has no גזלן. gazlan. No גזלן gazlan
at all. Okay. So anyway, that's the point. Now- so if the
dye is- if the dye is considered present, David has to- has
some way of paying Michael for the dye, because it's like he's
holding on to Michael's dye. And if the dye isn't present, then
there's no, you know- then there's no payment. תוספות Tosafot says there
should be some payment, you got some benefit out of me, but
let's bracket that. Certainly it's not considered like the dye is present,
so he doesn't have to pay Michael for the full value of
the dye. That's the question. Okay. Is Michael's dye seen to be
present in David's wool? Okay, it's integrated into the wool. Not present
means the dye has completely disappeared and it just left some coloration
but that's something else. No. Integrated in the wool means it is
present. Your dye is somehow mixed up in- my dye is somehow
mixed up in your wool and my dye is there. So if
you can't get it out, pay me for it. That's the idea
of יש שבח סמנים. yesh shevach samanim. אין שבח סמנים ein shevach
samanim is your dye has disappeared, it doesn't exist anymore. I'm just
left with colored wool. So I don't have to give you anything,
I don't have your object. Now then תוספות Tosafot would say, but
at least you should say you got some benefit out of me.
That's a different conversation, but I don't have your object. It starts
with that. Okay? Would you say סמנים samanim is remnant?
No, no, no. סמנים samanim is the dye, the- the pigment, whatever
word you want to call it. The שבח shevach is the keyword.
Is it considered like that the pre- I don't know, I can't
get into the language issue here. Okay, fine. All
right. So anyway- so
the מהלך mahalach is, yeah. Could you consider this almost that- it
could extend this into intellectual property in some ways, maybe, you know?
This... That—yeah, but that's not this. That's the point that תוספות Tosafot
is raising. תוספות Tosafot is raising the point of I got some
improvement even without there being a physical object. That's not the idea
of the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא's Gemara idea is, is it considered
that the physical object is still present? או דילמא אין שבח סמנים
על גבי צמר O dilma ein shevach samanim al gabei tzeumer or
do we say that the improvement of the dye is not present,
meaning David does not have any of Michael's dye in his wool?
Okay, he doesn't have like, it's not like the object is still
present, okay, דאמר ליה לית לך גבאי ולא כלום. de'amar lei leit
lach gabai velo kelum.
I don't have anything of yours, I don't know what you're talking
about, I have some nicer wool now but I don't have any
object of yours.
We're just framing what the נפקא מינא nafka mina of the question
would be. So one is the case of the monkey without a
גזלן gazlan and the other case is a גזלן gazlan who dyed
it, wants to give back both objects, and is he giving back
both objects or has he not given back the dye? תא שמע,
Ta shema, come and hear: בגד שצבעו בקליפי ערלה ידלק. Beged shetziv'o
beklifei orlah yidalek.
If you basically took a garment and you dyed it with the
shells from ערלה orlah fruit. Now רש"י Rashi says this has to
be a case where
the shells of the fruit, it's not actually—it doesn't mean like the
wood of a tree because only fruit is ערלה. orlah. Okay, but
you used the shells of the fruit, okay, and you derived some
dye from it and then you used it to dye a garment.
Is that garment אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah or not? Because ערלה orlah
is
אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. But the גמרא's Gemara going to get to
that. Okay, but the first thing is, so we have to establish
that ערלה's orlah אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, but even if ערלה's orlah
אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, maybe this isn't ערלה orlah anymore. Okay, this
is just dye, I'm not getting הנאה hana'ah from the ערלה. orlah.
Now maybe you could say I got הנאה hana'ah because I took
a garment that was worth five dollars and made it worth ten.
Okay, but fine, that was already עובר over on my איסור הנאה,
issur hana'ah, I improved the value of my property, but there would
be no reason I can't wear it now because the wearing is
not continuing to derive benefit because the ערלה orlah is no longer
present. So that's the question: is the ערלה orlah still present after
it's dyed the garment? Okay, so it seems like it is. This
is pomegranate and walnut. Oh, that's interesting, okay, good examples of fruit
that make dyes. Yeah, pomegranate and walnut. אלמא חזותא מילתא היא. Alma
chazuta milta hi. So now the גמרא's Gemara reframed it from יש
שבח סמנים yesh shevach samanim because that phrase of שבח סמנים, shevach
samanim, specifically the word שבח, shevach, improvement, is a very חושן משפט
דיני ממונות Choshen Mishpat dinei mamonot word, right? Who owes who the
money? חזותא מילתא Chazuta milta could be like a יורה דעה Yoreh
De'ah word, like an איסור issur word, right? Is it still present
so that I'm getting הנאה hana'ah from ערלה? orlah? So it's interesting
the shift of the language besides Aramaic and Hebrew. אלמא חזותא מילתא
היא, Alma chazuta milta hi, you see that even if it's just
appearance, it's still like it's present and you're still deriving benefit from
it. Okay, so אמר רבא, amar Rava, רבא Rava says, הנאה הנראה
לעינים אסרה תורה. hana'ah hanir'eh la'einaim assrah Torah. No, no, no, when
it comes to ערלה, orlah, the תורה Torah actually forbade like aesthetic
pleasure, like if it's too visible.
Okay, for ערלה, orlah, דתניא, detanya, ערלים לא יאכל, arelim lo ye'achel,
יאכל? ye'achel?
Is it? We should check. Okay, somebody can look that up. ויקרא
י"ט. Vayikra yod-tet. וערלתם
ערלתו את פריו. ve'araltem orlato et piryo. וערלתם
לא יאכל. ve'araltem lo ye'achel.
I'm inclined to trust you on this. וערלתם לא יאכל. ve'araltem lo
ye'achel. Okay, fine. Okay, ערלים לא יאכל, arelim lo ye'achel, which anyway
that phrase of 'shall not be eaten,' the passive is more used
for איסור הנאה issur hana'ah anyway according to the גמרא. Gemara. ערלים
לא יאכל, arelim lo ye'achel, it shall not be eaten. אין לי
אלא איסור אכילה, Ein li ela issur achilah, I only know you
can't eat it. מנין שלא יהנה ממנו, Minayin shelo yehaneh mimenu, how
do I know you can't derive benefit? ולא יצבע בו, Velo yitzba
bo, and you cannot use it to dye. ולא ידליק בו את
הנר, Velo yadlik bo et haner, and you cannot use it to
use as fuel for the lamp. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, וערלתם ערלתו
את פריו ערלים לא יאכל. ve'araltem orlato et piryo arelim lo ye'achel.
So all this double language וערלתם ערלתו ערלים... ve'araltem orlato arelim... לרבות
את כולם, lerabbot et kulam, to say all of them is forbidden.
So basically the גמרא's Gemara saying it's a special exception by ערלה.
orlah. Now I do have to say, by the way, this is—you
could say it's any word, יאכל ye'achel could have meant, I mean
from or anything, just said יאכל ye'achel for whatever. What are you
asking? How do we get—how do we know to לדרשן darshen exactly
this? That's always the question. חז"ל, Chazal, you know, but whatever, חז"ל
Chazal are—you know, if you—חז"ל Chazal aren't starting in a vacuum, they
have a sense of where they're going. Okay, anyway, but the point
is, this is really a much larger discussion, like—and
which we're not going to get into. Number one is, forget the
question of 'is the thing considered present,' there's another question which is,
is aesthetic pleasure considered pleasure? Okay, I cannot get pleasure from עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. Can I go and look at a gorgeous idol
and, you know, get aesthetic pleasure from the artistry of it? Is
that an איסור הנאה issur hana'ah of the תורה Torah or not?
Okay, is מראה, mareh, you know, and we basically rule that that's
only an איסור דרבנן issur derabbanan type of a pleasure. Okay, so
that's like one question, right? That's not a question of 'is it
present,' in the scenario I gave, the idol was totally present, but
is that considered a type of הנאה? hana'ah? Right? There's another question
here which is like— Is the ערלה orlah considered present in the
garment? Am I getting benefit from the ערלה, orlah, which is sort
of our question of חזותא מילתא? chazuisa milsa? So רבא's Rava answer,
like, oh, the תורה Torah אסר assur'd it here, הנאה נראה לעיניים,
hana'ah nireh l'einayim, you know, the נראה לעיניים nireh l'einayim seems to
be pointing more to the other point, like the תורה Torah even
אסר assur'd aesthetic pleasure, seems to be pointing to defining the type
of pleasure. But it seems regardless, his answer is, this is what
the תורה Torah is saying by ערלה. orlah. You can't learn out
from this to other cases, this is a special הלכה halacha by
ערלה. orlah. I don't understand how you get the answer of destroy
it. Okay, if you make it, how do you get from there
that if I did it, then I have to like destroy it?
Oh, because the מצוה, mitzvah, oh, that's a good point, meaning maybe
I'm not allowed to continue wearing it because my wearing it is
getting הנאה, hana'ah, but how do you know I have to destroy
it? Oh, okay, I misunderstood you. So that's a good question and
by the way, that's part of why the גמרא's Gemara bringing this
as a proof, because the מצוה mitzvah is, you know, to destroy
the ערלה, orlah, so I mean that's חז"ל Chazal learn out, okay,
but in order that's a separate question, but let's just take it,
you know, in general, okay, but if there's a מצוה mitzvah to
destroy ערלה orlah and now there's a מצוה mitzvah to destroy the
בגד, beged, what you're saying is more than just this included in
the איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, what you're saying is that the ערלה
orlah is still present. So Michael is absolutely correct to focus us
on the fact that the idea of destroying the בגד beged is
making a clearer statement than the איסור הנאה issur hana'ah that we're
seeing the ערלה orlah still present. How we get from this פסוק
pasuk to say because it's אסור בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, therefore, we seem
to say well, if the תורה's Torah going to say it's אסור
בהנאה assur b'hana'ah even if this state, presumably it's telling me that
it's still considered to be present. Okay, so but that's absolutely correct,
and but at the end of the day, רבא Rava said it's
a special הלכה halacha by ערלה, orlah, you can't learn it out
to other things, yes. So something like indigo where the dye comes
from the leaf don't have to worry about ערלה? orlah? Correct. Okay,
so רבא Rava says it's an ערלה orlah הלכה. halacha. Okay, it's
אסור בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, that's one thing, you know, aesthetic is considered
הנאה, hana'ah, it's אסור בהנאה assur b'hana'ah as Michael said, not only
is it אסור בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, from there we infer that it's
present and you have to destroy it, that's all an ערלה orlah
הלכה. halacha. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. Okay,
בגד שצבעו בקליפי שביעית, beged shetzva'o b'klipei shevi'is, let's say you use
שביעית shevi'is shells to do it. And by the way, we're going
to discuss in a minute because שביעית shevi'is also is, you know,
does that apply it doesn't apply to wood like you know wood
whatever like you know if you break off a branch of a
tree on שמיטה shemittah and you know using it for like firewood,
that doesn't have the status of שמיטה. shemittah. שמיטה's shemittah also doesn't
apply to indigo. Right. שמיטה, shemittah, well, take anyway, but we'll have
to figure out what type of dyes שמיטה shemittah applies to. But
nevertheless, let's move on. Okay, so you've got some type of a
wood or a dye that שמיטה shemittah applies through. Like a fruit?
Yeah, you could be like the other one, you use a fruit,
you used it to dye a garment. ידלק, yidaleik, you also have
to burn it. Now this is after the time of ביעור. bi'ur.
Right, there's a time when the fruit or whatever is no longer,
you know, out in the fields and the animals are no longer
eating it and then you have to destroy it if you have
it stored up in your home, because again שמיטה shemittah is supposed
to be for eating, not for storing, so after a time that
it's no longer available for eating you have to destroy it. So
anyway, you see it's not limited to ערלה, orlah, you see it's
considered to be present. So שאני התם דאמר קרא תהיה. shani hasam
d'amar kra tihyeh. It says, are we looking for a פסוק? pasuk?
Now I'm looking for a פסוק. pasuk.
קדש תהיה לכם. Kodesh tihyeh lachem. I think it's קדש תהיה לכם.
Kodesh tihyeh lachem. Okay. תהיה בהוייתה תהא, Tihyeh b'havyasoh tehei, it retains
its status. So again, a special הלכה halacha by שמיטה shemittah that
even after you dyed it, it's still considered to be present. So
basically, yes, those are pretty good cases, but we're going to make
them exceptions. Another way to also have said is maybe there's a
difference between the world of איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah and the world
of דיני ממונות. dinei mammonos. Right, again, that was that shift from
יש שבח סמנין yesh shevach samanin to the language of חזותא מילתא.
chazuisa milsa. But you've given me two examples about איסורי הנאה issurei
hana'ah and I'm going to say that's those are exceptions. Have you
an answer to her question? We have an answer. Now רבא, Rava,
now although he was quoted before and some say that before it
was רבה Rabbah not רבא, Rava, does this again, but actually thinks
that these are not exceptions. So now we're going to let's take
a look. רבא רמי, Rava rami, רבא Rava showed a contradiction. תנן,
Tnan, our משנה Mishna says, בגד שצבעו בקליפי ערלה ידלק. beged shetzva'o
b'klipei orlah yidaleik. אלמא חזותא מילתא היא. Alma chazuisa milsa hi. רבא
Rava started by assuming this wasn't an exception. No, that הלכה halacha
by ערלה orlah that you have to destroy it shows that it's
present and shows that even just the appearance is like the thing
is still there. ורמינהי, U'reminhi, I'll ask you on this. רביעית דם
שנבלעה בבית, Revi'is dam shenivle'ah b'bayis, if you have a רביעית, revi'is,
what's a
a quarter of a לוג, log, it's like a three and a
half ounces, all right, the minimum size for a קידוש Kiddush cup.
Okay, you got a three and a half ounces of blood of
a dead body. Now that's the amount of blood of a dead
body that causes טומאה tumah in an אוהל. ohel. If anything is
under the same roof with that, it becomes טמא. tamei. Now, what
happened is there was God forbid a murder in a house, okay,
or whatever, and blood got absorbed into the floor. Okay, into the
floorboards. All right, and a רביעית revi'is of blood got absorbed and
then you cleaned out the whole house, the body isn't there, whatever.
Is the blood still in the house? Is the blood still causing
טומאה tumah in the house? That's like a that's like I think
like the best case so far of of is it still present?
Yes, does it still cause new things that come into the house
to become טמא? Tamei? You'd have to then, right? I would then
rip up the floorboards, right? Okay, so רביעית דם שנבלעה בבית הבית
טמא. Reviis Dam SheNivla BeBayis HaBayis Tamei. So one teaching is the
house is טמא. Tamei. ואמרי לה הבית טהור. V'Amrei Lei HaBayis Tahor.
There's another version that the house is טהור. Tahor. ולא פליגי V'Lo
Pligi and we actually say these don't contradict. הא בכלים דבלע מעיקרא,
Ha BeKeilim DeVal Mei'ikara, if there were vessels before it got absorbed
in the house, then they're טמא Tamei because then it was not,
it was actually present. Okay, הא בכלים דאתו לבסוף, Ha BeKeilim DeAsu
LiBasof, but after it got absorbed and you bring new objects into
the house, the new objects do not become טמא. Tamei. So if
that's how you resolve it, the basic הלכה Halacha is that the
blood is not considered to be present. Okay, so נבלע בכסות, Nivla
BeKsus, now let's say it got absorbed into a garment. Okay, רואין,
Ro'in, you assess. אם מתכבסת הכסות ויוצא ממנה רביעית דם, Im MisKabeset
HaKsus Yotzei Mimenah Reviis Dam, if you could launder the garment and
extract a רביעית Reviis of blood, so a רביעית Reviis of blood
is extractable from the garment. Okay, and you could in the end,
you know, wring it out and you would have a רביעית Reviis
of blood be mixed up with your soapy water but you would
get a רביעית Reviis of blood out of it. Okay, this big
תוספות Tosafos is trying to figure out how you would determine that.
But anyway, אם מתכבסת הכסות ויוצא ממנה רביעית דם טמאה היא. Im
MisKabeset HaKsus Yotzei Mimenah Reviis Dam Tamei Hi. Then the garment is,
now Rashi says the garment's always טמא Tamei because the garment came
in contact with the blood before it got absorbed. But it means
the blood is still present and then if this blood is under
if this garment is under a roof it causes everything else to
become טמא. Tamei. Okay, so if the blood could be extracted, the
blood is still present. It'll be מטמא. MeTamei. Right, מטמא, MeTamei, that's
how the ב"ח Bach switches it to. Okay, or טמא, Tamei, I
don't know, no, just טמא. Tamei. ואם לאו טהורה, V'Im Lav Tehorah,
if not, טהורה. Tehorah. Anyway, so what do you see? You see
basically the הלכה Halacha is bracketing the case where the dye or
the blood is extractable. If it's not extractable, it's assumed that it's
not present. So when it comes to ערלה, Orlah, it's present and
you have to destroy the בגד. Beged. When it comes to טומאה,
Tumah,
bracketing the extractable case, it's not present. What's the הלכה? Halacha? They
contradict one another. So before we said ערלה Orlah is the
exception. Rava's going to say blood is the exception, טומאה Tumah is
the exception. אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, says רב כהנא, Rav
Kahana, מקולי רביעיות שנו כאן. MiKulei Reviyot Shanu Kan. We're talking about
a leniency about a רביעית Reviis of blood. Why? בדקי דם תבוסה
דרבנן. BeDkei Dam Tvuza DeRabbanan. It's talking about not blood that came
out after the guy had died. It was blood that was coming
out as the guy was dying. So
as the guy was dying. As the guy was expiring. Anyway, in
that case when you're not sure if the full amount, the full
amount of the רביעית, Reviis, the minimum amount came out after death,
it's possible the minimum amount did not come out after death, some
of it came out during life. So there it's a whole that's
called דם תבוסה. Dam Tvuza. It's a question what the status of
this blood is. That case, it's only דרבנן DeRabbanan that it causes
טומאה. Tumah. So we're going to be lenient and say if it's
absorbed it does not cause טומאה. Tumah. But if it was a
full רביעית Reviis of blood that came out after death and it
was absorbed in the floorboards, yes, it would still be present and
still cause טומאה. Tumah. So the גמרא Gemara on עמוד א' Amud
Aleph and the עמוד ב' Amud Beis have completely switched gears. The
גמרא Gemara on עמוד א' Amud Aleph was arguing חזותא לאו מילתא
Chazusa Lav Milsa and the case of ערלה Orlah is an exception,
a special פסוק Pasuk by ערלה Orlah you destroy it's present but
the rule is it's not present. This says the opposite. ערלה Orlah
is the rule, it is present, you destroy the בגד Beged of
the ערלה Orlah and this case of טומאה, Tumah, that's an exception.
But the basic הלכה Halacha is that yes, even after dye is
absorbed or blood is absorbed, it's considered to be present. Yes, I
know you don't want to go into the detail, but it's kind
of a broad way to give such an application, like it's the
same mindset, right? Like טעם כעיקר. Ta'am K'Ikar. Yeah, there definitely is
something similar, when is something still there? When is something still present?
Affects its environment?
Totally. Okay, so we haven't concluded. We have not had a conclusion.
We end it without a conclusion and now because we mentioned שמיטה,
Shemittah, we're going to turn a little bit to discussing what types
of things have קדושת שמיטה. Kedushat Shemittah. Do dyes have קדושת שמיטה?
Kedushat Shemittah? Yes. What were we saying with your blue shirt that
intuitively it's not there anymore. Here it's saying it is there. Yes,
that is correct. Okay, now again, maybe there's a different הלכה Halacha
between דיני ממונות Dinei Mamonot and איסורין, Issurin, right? The language is
interesting, switching from יש שבח סמנין Yeish Shevach S'manin into a language
of חזותא מילתא. Chazusa Milsa. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara turns to
שמיטה. Shemittah. רבא רמי, Rava Rami, רבא Rava showed another contradiction. תנן,
Tenan, ממין הצובעים, MiMin HaTzovim, there's a משנה Mishna that says that
any type of like plant or whatever or that's from a type
of a dye or whatever plants used for pigment are have קדושת
שמיטה. Kedushat Shemittah. So it says ממין הצובעים MiMin HaTzovim what would
be an example of that? ספיחי סטין וקוצה, Sefichei Satin VeKotza, so
if you have like a wild growth of סטין Satin and קוצה,
Kotza, what are those? According to Steinsaltz it's woad, it's used to
produce a dye chemically identical to indigo. Okay, we're back to our
indigo. What's the
סטין? Satin? Safflower. Safflower and woad. Okay, anyway so these are types
of plants, okay, יש
להם שביעית ודמיהם שביעית. Yeish Lahem Sheviis U'Dmeihem Sheviis. So they have
שביעית Sheviis and their money has שביעית. Sheviis. Even though here's the
point though, unlike ערלה, orlah, these are inedible, okay? They are they
are types of vegetation or plants or whatever that are used primarily
for dye and they are not edible. And even though they're not
edible, they have קדושת שביעית. kedushat shevi'it. יש להם שביעית ודמי שביעית,
Yesh lahem shevi'it u-demei shevi'it, and if you sold them, the קדושה
kedusha of the money would also have that status. יש להם ביעור
Yesh lahem bi'ur if they're they have to be destroyed after they're
no longer sort of the time of ביעור bi'ur of destroying it
has come, ודמי ביעור u-demei bi'ur and if they were sold then
the money has that הלכה halacha as well. So what do you
see? Even though they're inedible, they have קדושת שביעית. kedushat shevi'it. אלמא
עץ יש בו משום קדושת שביעית. Alma etz yesh bo mishum kedushat
shevi'it. It sounds like wood, stuff that's not edible that grows, has
קדושת שביעית. kedushat shevi'it. Okay, is that really true? ורמינהי U-reminhi I'll
ask you. עלי קנים ועלי גפנים, Alei kanim ve-alei gefanim, if you
have leaves, we're back to the leaves case now, of like of
like of what's a kind of reeds or leaves of or grape
leaves, שגבבן בחצר על פני השדה, she-gevavan be-chatzer al pnei ha-sadeh, if
you sort of collected them out in the field, okay, in order
to sort of store them, okay, but wait, this people are not
assuming that you eat grape leaves? Right, wait, but here's what it's
going to say. לקטן לאכילה, Liktan le-achilah, if you gathered them for
the purpose of eating, so you basically are treating them as food,
יש בהם משום קדושת שביעית, yesh bahem mishum kedushat shevi'it, then they
have קדושת שביעית kedushat shevi'it cause they're food. לעצים, Le-etzim, if you
gathered them to use as wood as firewood, אין בהם משום קדושת
שביעית. ein bahem mishum kedushat shevi'it. They don't have the קדושת שביעית.
kedushat shevi'it. So what is it? Here it's clear that stuff that's
not edible, not treated as food, doesn't have קדושת שביעית, kedushat shevi'it,
and by the case of dyes, even if it's not edible, it
has the קדושת שביעית. kedushat shevi'it. So what's the story? So we'll
just read the one answer and ומשני, u-meshani, here's the answer, אמר
קרא, amar kra, the verse says לאכלה. le-ochlah. It says you know,
תהיה כל תבואתה לאכלה, tihiyeh kol tevu'atah le-ochlah, לאכלה. le-ochlah. All of
the grain should be to eat. לאכול. Le-echol. So what's the לאכלה
le-ochlah pasuk? A different one. והייתה שבת הארץ לכם לאכלה. Ve-hayetah shabbat
ha-aretz lachem le-ochlah. Thank you. Okay, so the resting of the land
will be for you to eat. So okay, eat doesn't sound like
dyeing, so the other type of dyeing, so הנאה hana'ah so any
type of benefit of that is sort of of that is similar
to the experience of eating. So what does it mean? בהנאתו וביעורו
שווים. be-hana'ato u-vi'uro shavim. What happens when you eat food? The pleasure
you get from the food comes at the time it's being destroyed.
Okay, now why is that true by dyes and not true by
firewood? For the following reason. יצאו עצים שהנאתן אחר ביעורן. Yatz'u etzim
she-hana'atan achar bi'uran. It actually only explains the firewood. By firewood, okay,
if anybody ever tried to make a fire, I just was spent
a week in Vermont or whatever and had a couple of meals
by campfire, okay, you can't cook it as it's like when the
fire is high, but the best way is like after the fire
has died down and you've got the coals, right, so that the
basic benefit comes right when it's burning from when you're getting the
fire from the part that has already turned into charcoal, not from
the the stuff that's present. So that's considered to be the primary
benefit comes after it's been destroyed. Now how about the dyes? Where
does the benefit come after during the time it's being destroyed? So
here there's a debate of רש"י תוספות. Rashi Tosafot. רש"י Rashi says,
and we'll end with this, רש"י Rashi says four lines
from
the bottom, אבל ממין צבעים בשעת רתיחת היורה כלה השרש וקולט הצבע.
aval mi-min tzeva'im be-sha'at retichat ha-yoreh kalah ha-shoresh ve-koleit ha-tzeva. So the
when you're when you're when you're making the dye, remember we talked
about like putting the stuff into like into water and whatever, you're
getting benefit because the the the vegetation is being destroyed while it's
creating the dye. So רש"י Rashi says the benefit is that you
now have some dye. You destroyed some, you know, some bark or
whatever and you've and now you have dye. That's the benefit. תוספות
Tosafot has a different explanation. תוספות Tosafot says, if you look at
תוספות, Tosafot, he says שהנאתן וביעורן שוה she-hana'atan u-vi'uran shaveh right two
one line into that תוספות Tosafot middle line, he says אבל צבע
הנאתו וביעורו שוה aval tzeva hana'ato u-vi'uro shaveh why? דהנאתו כשלוובשן ואז
הוא כלה ומתבער. de-hana'ato k'she-lovshan ve-az hu kalah u-mitba'er.
When do I get the benefit from the dye? When I wear
my nice blue shirt. That's why I wear blue today. Okay, so
until that point, I wasn't deriving any benefit from it. But now
as I'm wearing it, well, my wearing of it is also the
process of destroying it, because as I'm wearing it, the dye is
slowly being used up or something. I don't know, which is crazy.
Like what? Like I bet you this whole shirt will fall to
pieces before the dye. Now that's not true. Some types of things
the dye does start to wear away. But that's a little funny.
That does not feel to me like the benefit and the destroying
are coming at the same time. So for some reason the גמרא
Gemara understands by dye let's take רש"י's Rashi's approach that as you
destroy the plant it transforms into this liquid type of dye and
that's considered you derived the benefit, you made something out of it,
okay, whereas by the wood the benefit is seen to come after
the wood is destroyed. So on based on some distinction which I
know to us seems pretty hair-splitting, but we're saying dyes have קדושת
שביעית, Kedushas Shvi'is, and wood does not. Okay, and we will pick
up with this tomorrow on שבת. Shabbos.